<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3.0//EN"
                      "https://docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<article revision="20251101">

  <title>XOM Design Principles</title>

 <articleinfo>
     <author>
      <firstname>Elliotte</firstname>
      <othername>Rusty</othername>
      <surname>Harold</surname>
    </author>
    <authorinitials>ERH</authorinitials>
    <copyright>
      <year>2002-2004, 2006, 2025</year>
      <holder>Elliotte Rusty Harold</holder>
    </copyright>
    <date>Novemeber 1, 2025</date>
  </articleinfo> 


 <para>
  I have a very clear vision for XOM
  based on certain principles for both XML and Java.
  If you want to request new features or contribute to its development,
  you should understand these first. They 
  go a long way toward explaining why XOM takes the path it does.
</para>

<sect1>
   <title>Design Goals</title>
   
   <para>
       The ultimate goal of course is an API that&rsquo;s useful for processing 
       XML with Java.
       However, there are many different ways to design such a thing, and sometimes you have to make trade-offs.
       The following are the basic goals for this API:
   </para>
   
    <sect2>
<title>Absolutely correct</title>

  <para>
    XOM will model XML completely and correctly.
    Most other APIs (with the notable exception of SAX)
    have made significant compromises in their XML support
    in the name of performance and other false gods.
    XOM will not. Nothing is more important in the design of XOM
    than XML correctness.
  </para>

</sect2>  
   
   <sect2>
<title>Easy to use</title>

  <para>
    The second goal, that is outweighed only by the first,
    is that XOM be easy to use. Developers should not need to be either XML or Java 
    experts in order to use XOM.
    The API should be intuitive, memorable, and consistent so that frequent reference to the documentation
    is not necessary. While the hard things should be possible,
    most developers spend most of their time doing relatively easy things. 
    Thus it is more important to make the easy tasks easier than to make the hard tasks easier.
  </para>

</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Easy to learn</title>

  <para>
    Ease of learning generally goes hand-in-hand with ease-of-use, and XOM is no exception.
    I've strived for a shallow learning curve. 
    Among other effects, 
    this means I've strived for loose coupling between classes and methods.
    Methods can be used and understood in isolation
    without reference to other methods.
    Most classes have the minimum connections they need with other classes.
    Everything outside the nu.xom package is optional
    and can be ignored by a first-time user.
    </para>
    
    <para>
    This also means that
    simplicity is a virtue, and that I've tried to keep the number of unnecessary 
    public methods and classes to
    a minimum, especially in the core API. The API documentation should not contain a lot of
    clutter that confuses and repels new users.  
  </para>

</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Fast enough</title>

  <para>
   As Donald Knuth wrote in 1974,
   <quote>premature optimization is
        the root of all
        evil.</quote><footnote>
        <para>
        Donald Knuth, 
        <citetitle pubwork="article">Structured Programming with 
        <literal>go to</literal> Statements</citetitle>, 
        <citetitle pubwork="journal">Computing Surveys 6</citetitle> 
        (1974): 261-301</para></footnote>
        
   XOM tries to be fast enough for most common uses.
   It certainly won&rsquo;t be as fast as SAX for many uses because 
   it depends on an underlying SAX parser to read the document. 
   XOM deliberately trades speed for convenience.
   it is focused on programmer productivity, not
   minimum execution time. 
  </para>

  <para>
    That said, I will of course look for opportunities to significantly 
    optimize XOM provided it affects neither the public API nor the fundamental correctness of 
    XOM&rsquo;s XML handling. 
  </para>
  
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Small enough</title>

    <para>
   In a similar vein I am not especially concerned about memory footprint.
   The footprint is extremely competitive with other tree-based APIs such as 
   DOM and JDOM. Indeed a XOM <classname>Document</classname> object is likely to be two to three times
   smaller than the corresponding JDOM or DOM <classname>Document</classname> object.
   However, memory size is not the major focus. 
   I did not make even the most basic measurements of memory usage
   until the API was well underway.
   First, I made XOM right.
   Then, I made it small and fast.
  </para>

</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>No gotchas</title>

  <para>
   XOM should not surprise.
   Every method should have a clear and precise name that 
   identifies what it does.
   Methods should do what&rsquo;s expected of them, and nothing else!
   </para>
   
   <para>
   If XOM does surprise, it should do so only because XML itself is surprising.
   For instance, many developers are surprised to discover they can&rsquo;t 
   create a <classname>Text</classname> object that contains
   nulls or vertical tabs.
   However, this is a restriction of XML.
   XOM cannot violate this and remain faithful to the XML specification.
   However, when such a surprise is unavoidable, XOM should throw an exception with
   a detailed error message at the first opportunity to make the problem very obvious.
   It should not allow developers to persist in their misunderstanding of XML.
  </para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>
   <title>Design Principles</title>
<sect2>
<title>As simple as it can be and no simpler!</title>

  <para>
    XOM strives to make XML as simple as it can possibly be, but no simpler!
    XOM cannot and does not paper over the real complexities of XML such as
    the differences between attributes and namespace declarations,
    the case and order significance of XML elements, or white space.
    It presents XML as it really is, warts and all. 
    It is my goal that whenever you see an ugly part of XOM, it is only because the corresponding part of
    XML is at least that ugly. 
  </para>

</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Use Java idioms where they fit</title>

  <para>
    XOM is a Java native API. It strives to adhere to good Java coding practices including:
  </para>
  
  
  <itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Naming conventions</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Proper return types for setters and getters</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Utility methods like <methodname>hashCode</methodname>, <methodname>equals</methodname>, 
and <methodname>toString</methodname>. </para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
    However, I have not carried this to an extreme.
    In particular, where the Java way of doing things seems fundamentally broken
    or just not appropriate for an XML API, I have felt free to
    invent my own solutions. These include:
  </para>
  
  <itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Using copy constructors and <methodname>copy</methodname> methods instead of <methodname>clone</methodname></para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Using XML instead of <interfacename>Serializable</interfacename></para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Using type-safe lists instead of the Java Collections API. </para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 
  
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>There&rsquo;s exactly one way to do it</title>

  <para>
    Simplicity is a virtue. While convenience methods
    seem useful in isolation, taken as a whole they often significantly clutter an API.
    A class with 80+ methods is simply too big to understand.
    One has to consider the developer&rsquo;s ability to understand the class as a whole,
    as well as each individual method.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    In general, I have added convenience methods only when the 
    need seemed very common and the 
    standard way of accomplishing the task was very cumbersome.
  </para>

  
  <para>
    If you find a particular need for some convenience method that I have not
    judged worthy of inclusion, it should be possible to write a subclass of the standard XOM classes
    that implements that method.
    In general, this will also require writing your own 
    <classname>NodeFactory</classname> subclass that instantiates instances of your subclass instead of 
    instances of the standard classes. 
  </para>

</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Start small and grow as necessary</title>

  <para>
   It is easier to add a feature than take one away.
   The initial release of XOM attempts to be as small as possible.
   I tried to keep public methods and classes to a minimum,
   especially in the 
   core nu.xom package.
   If I discover I've left anything significant out, I can always add it in later
   without breaking backwards compatibility.
  </para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>
   <title>Principles of API Design</title>

<sect2>
<title>APIs are written by experts for non-experts</title>

  <para>
  Aside from SAX and DOM, most XML APIs appear to have been written by experienced 
  programmers as they were learning XML.
  This may have helped them learn XML, but it didn&rsquo;t produce particularly high-quality APIs.
  Common problems included mishandling of white space,
  confusion of the XML declaration with a processing instruction,
  namespace malformedness, assuming that Unicode is a two-byte character set,
  and more. Before you begin to write an XML API, you really do need to understand XML at a much
  deeper and more technical level, than a typical XML user,
  much as an automotive engineer needs to know a lot more about an internal combustion engine
  than a casual driver or even an auto mechanic.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    One of the jobs of the expert or experts who design the API is to know better
    than the client programmers what they should be doing.
    It is the API&rsquo;s task to lead the client programmers in the right direction by making
    the right path easy and the wrong path difficult to impossible.
    At the extreme, it is the job of the expert  to tell the client programmers
    that they really don&rsquo;t want to do what they think they want to do,
    that they should do something else instead. 
  </para>

   <para>
    This can appear arrogant, and indeed it is.
    But this should be an arrogance built out of experience.
    It should be an arrogance that is earned and that can be respected.
  </para>

  
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>It is the class&rsquo;s responsibility to enforce its invariants</title>

  <para>
   Classes are responsible for enforcing their class invariants,
   not client programmers. Nobody who uses the public methods of a class should be assumed
   to understand  what is and is not legal.
   An object should be created in a correct and legal state,
   and thereafter it should not be possible to change the object&rsquo;s state 
   to something illegal, not even temporarily.
  </para>

  <para>
   In the context of XML, this means, for example,
   that an <classname>Element</classname> object must have a legal name,
   that a <classname>Document</classname> object must have a single root element,
   that the contents of a <classname>Text</classname> object cannot contain null.
   All of this must be enforced rigorously at all times. It may perhaps be temporarily violated
   during the execution of a method; but the public interface of a class
   must always show objects to be in a legal state, no matter what the client programmer does,
   up to and including subclassing.
  </para>

</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Verify preconditions</title>

  <para>
    In order, to guarantee class invariants,
    it is necessary to verify all preconditions on a method.
    For instance, a <methodname>setName</methodname> method must 
    check that its argument is a legal XML 1.0 name. 
    If the argument is illegal in any way, it should throw an exception to prevent the
    name from being changed to the illegal value.
  </para>

  <para>
    Such checks must be final. They cannot be overridden in subclasses.
    They cannot be turned off by a switch at runtime.
    They need to be built into the code at a very low level
    that cannot be removed short of forking the code base. 
  </para>
  
  <para>
    Post conditions do not need to be checked in this rigorous a fashion.
    Generally speaking, it is enough for the test framework to verify post conditions.
    Assuming the input satisfies all preconditions,
    the method should not be able to move the object into an inconsistent state.
    If it does so, this is a bug in the library and should be fixed.
  </para>
  
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Do not allow clients to do bad things.</title>

  <para>
    Clients occasionally request the ability to turn off the checks, either because they feel they don't need them or because they have a special case where they actually need to generate incorrect data. <emphasis>Don't let them!</emphasis>
  </para>


  <para>
    Clients that think they don't need the checks are almost always wrong. 
    Everyone (library authors included) makes mistakes. Throwing out the safety net 
   is not a good idea.</para>


<para> The usual reason given for turning off the checks is "performance". Interestingly, such requests rarely come accompanied by any actual measurements demonstrating that the checks are a significant part of the performance issues the client is encountering. As Donald Knuth wrote, "premature optimization is the root of all evil in programming". XOM is quite fast, and has been extensively optimized. While more optimization remains to be done, it is already faster than many competing libraries that do not perform as extensive verification. Speed issues should be addressed by profiling and optimization, not by removing functionality and safety. 
  </para>



<para> The second reason given for turning off the checks is that the client wants to process or generate bad data. They may indeed want this, but they shouldn't. Furthermore the library should not let them. The library authors have a responsibility not just to the one client of the library but to all clients of the library. Furthermore, they have a responsibility  to all users of the underlying technology not to break it. The library must not pollute the ecosystem on which the library depends.
A TCP/IP library should not allow malformed IP packets to be sent to the network. 
An XML library should not allow malformed XML to be created. The library must encourage correct use of the underlying technology and discourage incorrect use. 
  </para>

<para>
Think of it this way: it's like designing a car to run on the public roads. It's not just the driver of the car you have to worry about. You also have a responsibility to other drivers, pedestrians, insurance companies, and indeed everyone who breathes on this planet. Their needs sometimes outweigh the needs or desires of the driver. Now if the driver opens up the hood and manually disables the emission control system and various safety features, there's not much you can do about it, but you're not responsible for it either. But if you ship a car that spews noxious emissions and injures pedestrians as soon as the buyer drives it off the lot, you are responsible for that. If the car only does this when driven 75 mph or faster, you're still responsible for that, even if you put a warning in the owner's manual and the fine print of the sales contract saying, "Don't drive faster than 75 mph." It's much better to design the car so that proper operation doesn't rely on unenforced limits.
</para>

</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Hide as much of the implementation as possible. </title>

  <para>
   A general principle of object oriented programming is that the
   implementation should be hidden. Only the public interface matters.
   The client should neither know nor care what goes on inside the implementation
   as long as the interface behaves according to spec.
   This allows significant flexibility in implementation for performance improvements 
   in later development. It also keeps the API simpler, and thus easier for the 
   programmer to learn and use. 
  </para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Design for subclassing or prohibit it</title>

  <para>
    Unchecked, subclasses can easily violate constraints on the behavior of an object.
     Subclassing should not be a back door that allows effectively anything to happen.
     If careful thought has not been given to exactly how a class&rsquo;s subclasses should behave
     and what they are and are not allowed to change, then the class should be declared final.
     You can always remove that restriction later when you've had time to consider
     the issues raised by subclassing further.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    XOM is designed for subclassing. Most methods are declared final.
    However, a few selected methods are exposed through a protected API that allows subclasses
    to interpose themselves at key points in object creation and mutation. 
    Furthermore, subclasses can provide additional functionality such as convenience methods
    or non-XML support. However, subclasses cannot override the constraints enforced by the superclass.
    They can be more strict than their superclass. For instance, an <classname>HTMLTable</classname> class could require that
    the element name be <markup>table</markup>. However, it could not allow the name to contain spaces. 
  </para>
  

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Prefer classes to interfaces</title>

  <para>
    A direct result of many of the above principles is that a library such as XOM should be developed 
    using classes rather than interfaces. Interfaces simply cannot fulfill many
    of the requirements of a useful library. 
  </para>
  
  <para>There are two primary and pretty much unrelated reasons XOM relies on 
classes rather than interfaces:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Interfaces (and the corresponding factory methods) are harder to 
use than classes (and constructors).</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Interfaces cannot verify constraints on an object.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
Interfaces add an additional layer of indirection in programming. 
While additional layers of indirection can solve many problems, I've 
observed that they often lead to much confusion among programmers. A 
significant chunk of JDOM&rsquo;s ease-of-use relative to DOM comes from 
using classes and constructors rather than interfaces. Certainly some 
programmers are comfortable with this level of indirection, but I 
think they're a minority. They may well be the smartest and most 
talented programmers, but I still think they're a minority. Most 
programmers in my experience are much more comfortable with concrete, 
direct APIs.
</para>

<para>
There also interface problems that affect everyone. The biggest is 
that is difficult for interface-based code to determine which class 
it is actually using. In the ideal world, this shouldn&rsquo;t matter. Any 
implementation of the interface should be able to take the place of 
any other. In practice this simply isn&rsquo;t true. For instance, almost 
no DOM implementation is willing to accept or operate on nodes 
created by a different implementation. In my own work, I repeatedly 
encounter problems because TrAX loads a different XSLT processor than 
I was expecting. SAX is a little more stable, but I still often need 
to choose a particular parser rather than accepting any 
implementation of <interfacename>XMLReader</interfacename>. The claim of implementation independence 
is simply not reliable in practice. Like Java itself, programs that 
process XML and are based on interfaces are very much write once, 
test everywhere.
</para>

<para>
The second issue is even more important. Interfaces cannot verify 
constraints on an object. There is no way to assert in an interface 
that the name of an element must be a legal XML 1.0 name, or that the 
text content of an element cannot contain nulls and unmatched halves 
of surrogate pairs. You must rely on the good faith of implementers 
not to violate such important preconditions. My experience with DOM 
has taught me that this is not a sensible bet. In the DOM world, 
implementations routinely fail to check the constraints DOM requires 
them to check. Implementations routinely fail to behave as DOM 
requires them to behave. Sometimes this is out of ignorance. 
Sometimes it&rsquo;s a deliberate and knowing choice. Neither case is 
acceptable to me. If you're using XOM, you're guaranteed 
well-formedness, even with subclasses. I can only make that guarantee 
by using concrete classes that include final, non-bypassable code to 
check all constraints. If you can find a way to make XOM generate a 
malformed document, even by subclassing, then it&rsquo;s a bug and I 
want to know about it so I can fix it.
</para>

<para>
Let me also address a non-issue for XOM: different implementations. 
The classic use-case for interfaces instead of classes is to support 
different implementations of the same API, multiple SAX parsers for 
example. In the context of XOM, this would most likely mean using a 
different storage backend; for instance, a native XML database 
instead of strings in memory. This is an interesting use-case but it 
is one I have chosen not to support precisely because I cannot figure 
out how to reconcile it with the requirement that XOM guarantee 
well-formedness. If somebody invented a means of plugging in 
different storage engines without allowing well-formedness checks to be 
removed or bypassed, I'd consider it; but well-formedness comes 
first. If it isn&rsquo;t well-formed it isn&rsquo;t XML, and XOM is an XML API.
</para>

<para>
I also think that the proper interchange format between different 
systems such as a native XML database and a custom application is 
real XML, not a DOM object, not a XOM object, not an Infoset, but 
real XML. Different local contexts will have different needs. One API 
will not suit them all. We can let a thousand incompatible APIs 
bloom, as long they all talk to each other by sending and receiving 
well-formed XML. On the other hand, subsetting or supersetting XML is 
an interoperability disaster. It is precisely this that XOM&rsquo;s 
draconian focus on well-formedness is designed to avoid.
</para>

</sect2>


</sect1>

<sect1>
   <title>XML Principles</title>


<sect2>
<title>All objects can be written as well-formed XML text</title>

  <para>
    If it isn&rsquo;t well-formed, it isn&rsquo;t XML.
    Some XML APIs let you create objects that cannot possibly be serialized as 
    well-formed XML. XOM does not.
    (Or if it does, that&rsquo;s a bug; and please tell me so I can fix it.)
    Every node object in XOM is potentially either 
    a well-formed XML document or a piece thereof.
    In fact, XOM is even a little stricter than this. It actually requires 
    namespace well-formedness, not simple well-formedness.
  </para>
  

</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>It is impossible to create malformed documents</title>

  <para>
      At no time does XOM let you do anything that would make a document
      namespace malformed. You cannot add two attributes with the same name to the same element.
      You cannot use a name for an element that contains illegal characters. You cannot remove the 
      root element from a document. You cannot add control characters like null or vertical tab to a text node.
      Nothing you do can produce malformed XML.
  </para>

</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Validity can be enforced by subclasses</title>

  <para>
    XOM itself does not enforce validity.
    However, it is possible to subclass the standard XOM node classes
    such as <classname>Element</classname> to impose additional restrictions.
    This theoretically allows you to use XOM to create APIs that guarantee validity against some schema,
    whether that schema is a DTD, a RELAX NG schema,
    a W3C XML Schema language schema, or just an implicit set of rules.
  </para>

</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Syntax sugar is not represented</title>

<para>
  XOM does not provide any information about the syntax sugar in an XML document.
  None of the following are reported in any way:
</para>

  <itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>CDATA sections</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Quotes around attribute values</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>White space inside tags</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Character and entity references</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Attribute order</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Defaulted vs. specified attributes</para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
    You will of course get the content from all of these.
    You just won&rsquo;t be told, for example, whether the less than character
    was represented as &amp;lt; or &amp;0x3C; or even
    &lt;[![&lt;]]&gt;. You should not care about any of this.
    Code that does care about this is almost always 
    broken code. 
  </para>
  
  <para>
    The one notable exception are XML editors.
    XOM is not suitable for writing a source-level XML editor.
    However, this is really a very strange use-case.
    Editors really need their own API, and an API that is 
    suitable for editors is not really suitable for most other tasks.
  </para>
  
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
   <title>Java Principles</title>

<sect2>
<title>Not thread safe</title>

  <para>
    Thread safety is tough, and can have significant performance implications.
    I chose not to make any classes in XOM thread-safe. 
    The simplest way to use XOM in a thread-safe fashion is not to allow any XOM object to
    be referenced from more than one thread.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    If you have to use a XOM object in more than one thread, try to make it read-only
    after its initial creation; and do all the initial creation in a single thread.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    If that&rsquo;s not possible, then you'll just have to synchronize the object yourself.
    In my experience, though, a very small percentage of actual code really needs to do this.
    I chose not to slow down XOM (and likely introduce subtle bugs) 
    for the majority of cases that don&rsquo;t need to concern themselves with this.
  </para>

</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Classes do not implement <interfacename>Serializable</interfacename>; use XML.</title>

  <para>
    XML is itself a serialization format. In fact, it is a much cleaner, much more interoperable
    format than Java&rsquo;s object serialization.
    Using object serialization limits you to exchanging data only with other Java programs.
    Without a great deal of care and effort, it limits you to exchanging data only with other programs
    that use the identical version of XOM.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    XML, by contrast, can be used to exchange data with Python programs, DOM programs,
    Perl programs, C++ programs, C# programs, and far more.
    These programs can use the same or a different version of XOM.
    They can use other APIs like SAX, DOM, JDOM.
    Even human beings can easily read and work with the data using a simple text editor.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    Binary formats are bad in general, and  
    Java&rsquo;s object serialization is far from the best binary format.
    Object serialization routinely violates access protection,
    interferes with class loading, breaks various design patterns,
    is slow as spit, 
    and in general causes far more problems than it solves. XML is far cleaner, 
    more reliable, more robust, and faster.
    Use XML.
  </para>

</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Classes do not implement <interfacename>Cloneable</interfacename>; use copy constructors.</title>

  <para>
    The <interfacename>Cloneable</interfacename> interface
    is a huge honking mess.
    It tries to implement the mix-in pattern in Java, but fails.
    Just because a class implements <interfacename>Cloneable</interfacename>
    is no guarantee you can actually clone it, 
    or even that it has a publicly accessible
    <methodname>clone</methodname> method.
    (On this point, see 
    <citation><citetitle pubwork="book"><ulink url="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ISBN%3D0201310058/ref%3Dnosim/cafeaulaitA/">Effective 
    Java</ulink></citetitle>, <author>
      <firstname>Joshua</firstname>
      <surname>Bloch</surname>
    </author>,
Addison-Wesley, 2001, ISBN 0-201-31005-8, pp. 45-52.</citation>)
  </para>
  
  <para>
    Consequently XOM classes do  not implement <interfacename>Cloneable</interfacename>.
    Instead each node class provides  a copy constructor 
    and a <methodname>copy</methodname> method.
    For example, the following code clones an <classname>Element</classname> object <varname>e</varname>:
  </para>
  
  <informalexample><programlisting>Element copy = new Element(e);</programlisting></informalexample>

  <para>
    If you have a node whose more specific type is unknown,
    you can use the <methodname>copy</methodname> method instead:
  </para>
 

  <informalexample><programlisting>Node copy = node.copy();</programlisting></informalexample>
  
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Lack of generics really hurts in the Collections API. Hence, don&rsquo;t use it.</title>

  <para>
    The Java Collections API is insufficiently type-safe. Although you can design a <classname>List</classname>
    subclass that only allows particular types of objects, all nodes for example,
    there&rsquo;s no way to indicate this in the subclass&rsquo;s API.
    All the <classname>List</classname> methods merely return and take as arguments objects of type
    <classname>Object</classname>. (Yes, starting in Java 1.5 generics are possible.
    However, not only am I unwilling to limit XOM to Java 1.5 and later.
    There are a number of compromises made in Java' 1.5's generics implementation
    for reasons of backwards compatibility that limit its type safety.)

    <!-- JDJ ref???? approximately dec. 2002-->
    </para>
   
   <para>
    Consequently, XOM uses its own list classes such as <classname>Nodes</classname>
    that are typed as strongly as possible. Furthermore, parent nodes such as 
    <classname>Element</classname> and <classname>Document</classname> do not
    contain a list. Instead, they are lists. They have their own append and insert and getChild
    methods. 
  </para>
  <note>
  <para>
    Internally, XOM actually does make quite heavy use of the Java Collections API.
    However, the adapter design pattern is used to completely hide this fact from client programmers.
  </para>
</note>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Problems detectable in testing throw  runtime exceptions</title>

  <para>
  I got this idea from Bruce Eckel (<ulink url="http://www.mindview.net/Etc/Discussions/CheckedExceptions">Does
  Java need Checked Exceptions?</ulink><footnote>
        <para>
        Bruce Eckel, 
        <citetitle pubwork="webpage"><ulink url="http://www.mindview.net/Etc/Discussions/CheckedExceptions">Does
  Java need Checked Exceptions?</ulink></citetitle></para></footnote>, 
) and Joshua 
Bloch  (<citation>Effective Java</citation>, 
particularly Item 40&mdash;Use checked exceptions 
for recoverable conditions and runtime exceptions for programming 
errors<footnote><para><citation>
<citetitle pubwork="chapter">Use checked exceptions 
for recoverable conditions and runtime exceptions for programming</citetitle>
    <citetitle pubwork="book"><ulink url="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ISBN%3D0201310058/ref%3Dnosim/cafeaulaitA/">Effective 
    Java</ulink></citetitle>, <author>
      <firstname>Joshua</firstname>
      <surname>Bloch</surname>
    </author>,
Addison-Wesley, 2001, ISBN 0-201-31005-8, pp. 172-173.</citation></para></footnote>&mdash;and 41&mdash;Avoid unnecessary use of checked exceptions<footnote><para><citation>
<citetitle pubwork="chapter">Avoid unnecessary use of checked exceptions</citetitle>
    <citetitle pubwork="book"><ulink url="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ISBN%3D0201310058/ref%3Dnosim/cafeaulaitA/">Effective 
    Java</ulink></citetitle>, <author>
      <firstname>Joshua</firstname>
      <surname>Bloch</surname>
    </author>,
Addison-Wesley, 2001, ISBN 0-201-31005-8, pp. 174-175.</citation></para></footnote>). 
Bloch 
is especially clear that precondition violations should cause runtime 
exceptions. (Think of <exceptionname>IllegalArgumentException</exceptionname>). 
Most of the time this indicates a programming error. Thus rather than 
putting in a try-catch block to handle the exception, the programmer 
should fix the mistake that led to the programming error in the first 
place. Assuming the programmer has fixed the mistake, there&rsquo;s no 
reason to catch the exception because it won&rsquo;t be thrown. And if the 
programmer&rsquo;s wrong, and they haven&rsquo;t fixed their mistake, then they 
should learn about it as soon as possible rather than having the 
exception get lost in an empty catch block added just to make the 
compiler shut up about an uncaught exception.
</para>

<para>
Most of the runtime exceptions in XOM occur as a result of 
precondition violations, for instance passing a string to <methodname>setName</methodname>
that is not a legal XML name. This will likely happen every time the 
program is run, or every time the program executes a particular 
section of code, rather than depending on input or temporary 
conditions. This isn&rsquo;t always true. For instance, a GUI might ask a 
user to type in an element name and then pass that string to <methodname>setName</methodname>. 
Whether or not the exception is thrown would then depend on what the 
user typed. However, I think far more often than not such a precondition 
violation is internal to the program, and thus should be caught by 
testing.
</para>

<para>
On the other hand, not all problems are like this. For instance, a 
<exceptionname>ParsingException</exceptionname> 
is thrown when an external document is discovered to 
be malformed. There is no way to predict this in advance because the 
document is not part of the program itself (unlike the string passed 
to <methodname>setName</methodname>). Whether or not the exception is thrown depends 
completely on which document you're parsing, and the document may not 
even exist at compile time. There&rsquo;s no way to tell if it&rsquo;s 
well-formed or not until run time. Hence <exceptionname>ParsingException</exceptionname>  
is a checked exception.
  </para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Assertions that can be turned off are pointless</title>

  <para>
  In Java 1.4 you can use a command line flag to disable assertion 
checking. However, if an assertion is violated, it&rsquo;s still an error, 
just one you no longer notice. Turning off assertions at runtime is 
like including airbags in a new car model during design and street 
testing, then removing them before you begin selling the cars to 
consumers. No matter how rigorously you test, the users of your 
library will encounter situations and uncover bugs you did not find 
in testing. As Rolf Howarth wrote on the java-dev mailing list 
back in February, 2002:
</para>

 <blockquote>
   <para>
programmers love the concept of assertions so much because it's like 
having your cake and eating it. On the one hand you can kid yourself 
you're protecting yourself by testing for error conditions that you 
know you should, but on the other you're absolved from any 
responsibility if the extra checks have a performance impact because 
they won't be there in production code. Except of course people 
usually leave assertions turned on in practice, certainly once 
they've been through the loop of puzzling over obscure bug reports 
from the field and muttering <quote>that can't happen, that assertion check 
should have picked that case up</quote>, just before their face turns white 
and they realise assertions are compiled out!
</para>
 </blockquote>

<para>
Consequently, I decided not to rely on Java&rsquo;s new assertion mechanism 
for precondition checking in XOM. Instead, each method that sets or 
changes some value verifies all preconditions explicitly and throws a 
runtime exception (normally a subclass of <exceptionname>XMLException</exceptionname>) if it detects 
a problem.
</para>

<para>
Furthermore, many methods are declared final to prevent subclasses 
from turning off this checking. Subclasses can override the various 
protected check methods to add assertions of their own, but they 
cannot remove the assertions in the core classes.
  </para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Setter and mutator methods return void</title>

  <para>
  Simple, clean, easy-to-use APIs eschew side-effects. Each method call should perform
  one complete, logically unified operation. It should do as much as the operation requires and no more.
  This knife cuts in both directions. A public method should not do less than one 
  operation (which would leave an object in an inconsistent state), 
  but it should not do more either. Getting, setting, incrementing, and changing an object 
  are logically distinct operations. In most cases, there is no semantic reason for a setter
  or mutator method to return a value. These methods should return void. 
  </para>
  
<para>
 Partially, this is based on my 
experience with JavaBeans, where returning void is necessary for a 
method to be recognized as a property setter. However, more 
importantly, it&rsquo;s semantically the right thing to do. By invoking a 
setter method (or any adder or mutator method) you are changing an 
existing object. You are not creating a new object. You are not 
getting a reference to some value that you did not have before. 
Nothing has been created that did not exist before. There is no 
justification for returning anything.
</para>

  
  <para>
    Some APIs such as JDOM have setter methods that return the object 
    whose property was set. This enables code to use method call chaining.
    For example,
  </para>
  
  <informalexample><programlisting>Element root = (new Element("html"))
    .appendChild(new Element("head"))
    .appendChild(new Element("body"))</programlisting></informalexample>

 <para>
    However, this is logically unjustified. It complicates the API
    and muddies the semantics of the method in exchange for syntactic
    convenience. It confuses the levels. 
  </para>

  <para>
    Even syntactically, I  don&rsquo;t like this style of coding.
    It&rsquo;s often unclear, even with good indentation, which nodes
    are being added where. Multilevel hierarchies rely too
    much on parentheses to specify what goes where.
    When the statement has executed you often don&rsquo;t 
    have reference variables pointing to the nodes you need.
    Plus it's harder to debug when single stepping through the code,
    because each statement does many separate tasks, and return values are
    not stored in inspectable intermediate variables.
  </para>
  
 <para>
Dividing this statement up into multiple relatively atomic operations 
makes the code cleaner, easier to read, easier to understand, and easier to debug. Yes, 
there are classes in the Java class library that don&rsquo;t operate this 
way, most notably <classname>StringBuffer</classname>. Perhaps this makes sense for 
<classname>StringBuffer</classname>, where it&rsquo;s basically the equivalent of the + operator. 
Honestly though, this is really just a sop thrown to performance to 
avoid allocating lots of extra strings. Logically, the plus operator 
should do what it does for numbers: return a new object that is 
neither of its operands.
 </para>
  
  <para>
    But even if I liked this style of coding, I'd still think that
    a setter method that returns the object whose property was set was 
    semantically wrong.
There is simply no logical justification for a setter or mutator 
method returning the object itself. It is a crutch designed to 
support a particular programming idiom, but that idiom is neither 
necessary nor helpful. Method call chaining is not an improvement.  
  </para>
  
</sect2>

</sect1>


<sect1>
   <title>Development Style</title>

<sect2>
<title>This is a cathedral, not a bazaar</title>

  <para>
    XOM has a single unifying vision, mine.
    I am absolutely open to criticism of and suggestions about 
    the API. Indeed the first eight development releases show some major changes 
    made as a result of user feedback.
    Suggestions were made, I considered them, and I decided they were valid points
    that needed to be addressed in the API.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    However, in all cases, I am the final arbiter.
    If I don&rsquo;t think something&rsquo;s a good idea, then it isn&rsquo;t going in, no matter 
    how many people are crying out for it.
    XOM  is a more-or-less benevolent dictatorship,
    not a democracy. I am the only committer.
    This is my API, and it reflects my thoughts and desires.
    In general, I think that APIs that come out of a single vision
    work much better than APIs designed by committee.
    (DOM is an extreme example of an API designed by committee and majority vote.)
  </para>
  
  <para>
    Of course, XOM is open source, so if you think I'm being a putz in not
    accepting your changes, you're free to fork and try to convince others than your variant is better
    than mine. With implementation experience you might even convince me
    to adopt your changes back into the main tree (which I have permission to do
    since XOM is released under the LGPL). 
  </para>

</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Unit testing</title>

  <para>
    Unit testing is essential for finding bugs.
    XOM currently includes over several dozen test classes,
    containing over 700 test methods, which probably test several thousand different things.
    A few tests really stretch the boundaries of the notion of unit test.
    For example one test runs the entire XInclude test suite, and two others
    canonicalize all well-formed documents in the XML 1.0 test
    suite, both with and without comments.  
    This has been essential for finding and fixing bugs, as well as for making changes without
    breaking things. 
    Tests are present to verify correct behavior, and to make sure the right exceptions are thrown when
    incorrect behavior is encountered.
    <ulink url="http://www.junit.org/">JUnit</ulink>
    is the testing framework of choice.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    Code coverage tools have been used to verify that the test suite 
    is indeed exercising the entire code base. Clover and Jester have been particularly helpful
    in this regard. Both have uncovered numerous bugs in previously untested code.
    They have also resulted in  elimination of substantial chunks of dead, unreachable code.
  </para>
  
   <para>
    Unit testing has also been found to make debugging much easier. The most significant contribution
    is  a convenient place to put a small test that exposes any newly reported bug.
    This allows one to set a break point and begin single stepping through 
    the right section of code with the right conditions when the problem is not immediately
    obvious. 
  </para>


</sect2>


<sect2>
<title>Static  testing</title>

<para>
Throughout the development of XOM, I've made frequent use of various static code checking tools.
All of these are imperfect to say the least, but they've all found significant 
bugs at one time or another. These include:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para><ulink url="https://pmd.github.io/">PMD</ulink></para></listitem>
  <listitem><para><ulink url="https://findbugs.sourceforge.net/">FindBugs</ulink></para></listitem>
  <listitem><para><ulink url="https://www.eclipse.org/">Eclipse IDE</ulink></para></listitem>
  <listitem><para><ulink url="https://openjdk.org/projects/code-tools/doccheck/">doccheck</ulink></para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>


</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Massive samples</title>

  <para>
    As part of the design of the XOM API, I reimplemented almost every example from
    <ulink url="https://www.cafeconleche.org/books/xmljava/">Processing XML with Java</ulink>
    in XOM. 
    (A few utility classes that were very specific to a particular API, and didn&rsquo;t really make sense
    for XOM, were omitted.)
    This helped me see what I had left out as well as what I had included that wasn&rsquo;t actually necessary.
  </para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

</article>
